本字幕由诸神字幕组出品，仅供学习交流
更多中日双语字幕，尽在www.kamigami.org 及微博@诸神字幕组
日听&翻译
小伍
sora
兰樱
校对
小江
mam
Askriios!
片源
Rei
时间轴
电池雪糕
压制
久嘉
Coolkid
戦闘用意
アストリオース
Yashasuiin!
突撃
ヤシャスィーン
Pars Era
Pars Era, the year 317.
パルス暦３１７年
"Maryam"
"Pars"
When their ally, Maryam,
was invaded by the Lusitanian army,
友邦マルヤム国に侵攻したルシタニア軍に対し
Pars responded on this day
この日　パルスは国王アンドラゴラス三世の指揮の下
by meeting them with a force 300,000 strong
under the command of their king,
Andragoras Ill, and crushed them.
３０万の軍勢で迎え撃ち　撃破
They built a mountain of
the Lusitanian troops' corpses.
ルシタニア兵の屍の山を築き上げた
字幕
诸神字幕
亚尔斯兰组
Come, once more!
さあ　もう一つ
Why, you!
この…
Now, above!
はい　上
Now, middle!
はい　中
Now, above!
はい　上
Now, below!
はい　下
Now, above!
はい　上
You are terrible, Vahriz.
Using a maneuver like that on me!
ひどいな　ヴァフリーズ
そんな技を使うなんて
この程度のものは技とは申しませぬ
Such trifling moves would
not be considered a maneuver.
They were merely fundamental sword strokes.
ただの　剣の基本動作です
However, if you do not
cultivate those fundamentals,
ただし　その基本を鍛えなければ　技も威力を失います
your maneuvers will be less powerful as well.
Hone those fundamentals, Prince Arslan.
基本をお磨きなさいませ　アルスラーン殿下
It is no fun.
つまらない
Why did you not accompany my lord
father on his campaign, Vahriz?
なぜ　ヴァフリーズは父上の遠征に同行しなかったのだ
Safeguarding this place,
the Royal Capital of Ec—batana,
ここ　王都エクバターナの守護が
is the duty that I have been
assigned upon this occasion.
此度　私に与えられた任務です
"Supreme General, Kingdom of Pars
Vahriz"
It is not only Lusitania to the west.
西のルシタニアのみならず
"Supreme General, Kingdom of Pars
Vahriz"
Kingdoms to the east have
their eyes upon this city as well,
東方の国々もこの都を狙っておりますゆえ
so we mustn't let our guard down.
油断はなりませぬ
If you are so busy, you needn't
give me daily sword lessons.
そんなに忙しいなら
毎日　私に　剣の稽古など　つけてくれなくてもよいのに
Speaking with such lackluster ambition,
そのような覇気のないことをおっしゃられていては
you will never become a fine king.
立派な王にはなれませぬぞ
Even simply mastering the
fundamentals of the sword
剣の基本ができているだけでも
will show in how you carry
yourself straight and tall.
立ち居振る舞いがしゃんとして見えるものです
And you have yet to embark
upon your maiden battle,
それに殿下は　初陣もまだですから
so you must practice the sword
in preparation for that day.
その日に備えて剣を鍛えておきませんと
I know this.
分かっているよ
I know this, but...
分かっているけど…
If you know it, then look sharp.
分かっておられるなら　きりっとなさいませ
The soldiers are waiting as well.
兵たちも待っております
Your service does you great credit.
大儀である
"Queen, Kingdom of Pars
Tahamenay"
I hope for much to come of
your eternal allegiance to Pars.
永遠なるパルスへの忠誠を期待します
Oh... uh...
To Her Majesty the Queen
and Prince Arslan! Salute!
王妃様とアルスラーン殿下に敬礼
Lady Mother!
母上
What is it, Arslan?
なんです　アルスラーン
Oh, no...
あぁ　いえ
I am sorry to have kept you waiting.
お待たせして　申し訳ありませんでした
Not at all. It seems you
practice the sword every day.
いいえ　毎日剣の稽古をしているそうですね
は…はい
Yes. I am working hard in order to
become a fine king like my lord father,
父上のような立派な王になるために励んではいるのですが
but my progress has been slow.
Vahriz is always--
なかなか上達いたしません
I see.
いつも　ヴァフリーズに…
そう
What does it mean to become a fine king?
立派な王になるとは　何なんだろうな
Azrael!
アズライール　スルーシ
Soroush!
Ah! If they have returned, then...
ほう　こやつらが帰って来たということは…
Come!
おいで
Your Highness!
殿下
Welcome home, Azrael.
おかえり　アズライール
Your Highness.
殿下
And Lord Vahriz. I trust I find you unchanged?
ヴァフリーズ殿も　お変わりありませんか
Kishward, you have returned.
キシュワード　戻ったのか
So, upon their return, they greet not
their master, but Your Highness first.
飼い主より先に殿下に帰還の挨拶とは
The cheeky bastards.
生意気なヤツらめ
They have no respect for you.
なめられているな
"Cavalry Captain, Kingdom of Pars
Kishward"
Oh, no, it is not that they do not respect me,
いえいえ　私がなめられているのではなく
"Cavalry Captain, Kingdom of Pars
Kishward"
but that they hold the deepest
affection for His Highness.
こいつらが心の底から　殿下を慕っているのです
獣や鳥は相対する人物の心を映す鏡
Birds and beasts are mirrors
that reflect what is in the heart of
those they come face-to-face with.
They know the soundness of
His Highness's heart and mind.
殿下の心の健やかさをこやつらは分かっているのです
遠征　ご苦労であった　皆　無事か
Your service on the campaign
is appreciated. All are safe?
Yes, sir.
はっ　当方の損害は軽微にて
Our losses were negligible.
Our Pars forces crushed the Lusitanian army
友邦マルヤムに侵入したルシタニア軍を
that invaded our ally Maryam.
我がパルス軍が撃退いたしました
His Majesty, King Andragoras, is returning.
アンドラゴラス陛下のご帰還です
"Cavalry Captain, Kingdom of Pars
Kharlan"
Lord Marzbān Kharlan!
マルズバーン・カーラーン様
"Cavalry Captain, Kingdom of Pars
Kharlan"
--How gallant!
--Lord Kharlan!
かっこいい
カーラーン様
"Cavalry Captain, Kingdom of Pars
Kharlan"
The one over there is Lord Marzbān Kubard.
あっちはマルズバーン・クバード様だ
"Cavalry Captain, Kingdom of Pars
Kharlan"
He's drinking again.
また　酒飲んでるぞ
Is he ever sober?
あの人　シラフのときあんの
Did you know?
知ってる　あの左目の傷は竜と戦ったとき　付いたんだって
That scar over his left eye is
from when he fought a dragon.
That's a lie.
うそつけ
My favorite is still Lord
Twin-Blade General Kishward!
俺は　やっぱり双刀将軍キシュワード様だよ
When I grow up, I'm going
to join the cavalry, too,
大きくなったら俺も騎兵隊に入って　王様をお守りするんだ
and I'm going to protect the king.
You dummy! Like the king
needs anyone to protect him.
バ～カ　王様がお守りなんか　いるかよ
He brought down a lion at the age of thirteen!
１３歳で獅子を倒してるんだぞ
Yeah, that's true.
そうだよな
Prisoners?
捕虜か
They're Lusitanian soldiers.
ルシタニア兵だわ
They're the ones who fight for their god, right?
神のために戦うってやつでしょう
The Cult of Yaldabaoth, was it?
イアルダボート教か
I hear they kill anyone who doesn't
share their beliefs, even babies.
異教徒は　赤子までも皆殺しにするんだと
How barbaric.
野蛮ね
H-Hey!
That's a child!
子供じゃねぇか
Lusitania sends even children like that into war?
あんな子供まで戦に出すのかい　ルシタニアは
Poor thing. What are his parents doing?
かわいそうに　親は何をやってるんだろうね
Your Highness.
殿下
Lord Father, I am most gl'ad to see you safe.
父上　ご無事で何よりです
The fighting was off in
distant lands and I worried--
遠い地での戦で　心配しており…
Defeat was never a possibility.
負けるはずもない
Vahriz, report to me of the
goings-on during my absence.
ヴァフリーズ　留守中の報告をせよ
Yes, sir.
はっ
What about Prince Arslan?
アルスラーン王子は？
He's so timid.
頼りないなぁ
We'll just have to protect him, huh?
俺たちが守ってやんなくちゃだな
Yeah.
だな
A young one.
若いヤツだ　力仕事できるヤツが欲しいんだ
I want one that can do physical labor.
王子
My prince, entering too far
into such quarters is...
あまり　このような場所に立ち入られるのは…
Why? This is a great opportunity
to speak to Lusitanians.
なぜ　せっかくルシタニア人と話せる機会ではないか
If you require slaves,
we could send a messenger.
奴隷が必要なのでしたら　使いの者に
No, I wish to hear for myself.
いや　自分で聞いてみたいのだ
About the kingdoms out there.
Of the people out there.
外の国のこと　外の人間のこと
You bastard! Do as you're told!
このやろう　言うこと聞きやがれ
What is the matter?
どうしたのだ
Why, Prince Arslan!
これは　アルスラーン殿下　このようなむさ苦しい所に
What brings you to these shabby quarters?
Are these men the ones from Lusitania?
この者たちがルシタニアの？
Yes, sir.
はい
Hello. If possible, I would
like to speak with you a bit.
こんにちは
できれば　少し君たちと話がしたいんだ
ちょ…ちょっと
Hey!
こらっ　なんてことしやがる
What the hell are you doing?!
Are you all right?
大丈夫ですか
Yes...
ああ…
You're all slaves now!
てめぇらは　もう奴隷なんだ
If you want to live, do as you're told!
生きていたけりゃ従え　分かったか
Got that?!
Aw, it's a kid.
なんだ　子供だ
Come on, let's not do this after all.
なあ　やっぱり　やめようよ
What're you saying? We're here already!
なんだ　今更
You're going to join the cavalry, right?
お前　騎兵隊に入るんだろ　びびってどうする
How can you get scared?
Let's give him a good thrashing,
so he'll never defy us Parsians again!
俺たちパルス人に逆らえないように　ガツンとやってやろう
H-Hey!
Such barbaric folk...
あんな野蛮な連中
If something were to happen to you,
there would be no going back.
王子の身に何かあってからでは遅いのですよ
lam not stupid, either. I will be careful.
私もバカではない　気をつけるよ
H-Help!
た…助け…
Wait here, my prince.
王子　お待ちを
H-Hey!
Stay back!
来るな
Or I'll kill him.
こいつを殺すぞ
Say, is there any chance I
could get you to let him go?
なあ　お主　そやつを放してやってはくれぬか
そうか　だったら…
Yeah? In that case...
Oh, wait!
あっ　ちょっと
Ow...
痛てっ　ちょっ…
Wait...
What was that?
なんだ
何事だ
‘Wﬁat happened?!
My goods ran away!
商品が逃げた
--What?!
--Oh, I mean...
何
ああ　いや　逃げただけならいいんだが…
If all he did was run away,
I wouldn't mind, but...
The prince...
王子が…
He protected us...
俺たちをかばって…
What?!
何
Find him!
捜せ
Yes, sir!
はっ
Hey, now, what's going on?
おいおい　何があったんだ
The west side!
西側だ
Don't let him get away!
逃がすな
What is this ruckus?
なんの騒ぎだ
Lord Daryun!
ダリューン様
What is it?
どうした
It's Prince Arslan!
アルスラーン王子が…
There he is!
After him!
いたぞ
Ow, ow...
追え
痛い…痛っ
There he is!
いたぞ
止まれ
Stop!
Let him go!
その方を放せ　もう逃げられんぞ
There's nowhere to run now!
寄るな　寄れば　こいつの首をへし折るんだ
Don't come any closer!
Come any closer and I'll break his neck!
If you don't want to die, run!
死にたくなかったら走れ
What?
--What?!
--Prince...
何
王子
Come!
来い
Huh? What?
あれ　すまぬ
--My apologies!
--Run, you slowpoke!
走れ　のろま
アルスラーン王子
Prince Arslan?
Damn it!
くそっ
This is bad. If this gets
reported to the palace...
まずいぞ　こんなことが宮殿に伝わったら…
Hey, which way did he go?!
おい　どっちに行った
All right! Hurry!
よし　急げ
Yes, sir!
はっ
あれほどの人数で追ってくるとは
Coming after me with that many men...
You must be the pampered son
of a prominent family.
貴様　いいとこの坊ちゃんだな
Looks like I made the right choice
switching hostages to you.
人質を貴様に代えて　正解だったようだ
Are you unharmed?
大事ないか
Thanks. You saved m...
すまない　助かった
What the hell is this long-necked creature?!
なんだ　この首の長い生き物は
Have you never‘seen one?
見たことないのか
The masters of entertainment
bring them by all the time.
興行師がよく連れてくるぞ
Is it a creature that lives in these parts?
この辺りにいる生き物なのか
さあ
No idea.
No idea? You're a useless one.
｢さあ｣って　使えないヤツ
--Come!
--O-Owowow!
来い
い…痛てっ
なんと豊かな国だ
What a rich kingdom.
This place is overflowing
with people and things.
物と人があふれ返っている
ここは大陸公路の中心だからな
We are at the heart of the
Continental Highway, after all.
パルス人は飢えを知らず　文化的に豊かに暮らしている
Parsians know no hunger and
lead prosperous, cultured lives.
Where to now?
今度はどこに
Never mind that! Go up!
いいから上がれ
You seem to have a lot of slaves.
奴隷が多いようだが
それはそうだ
But of course, we do.
奴隷の多さは　この国の豊かな証拠だ
The large number of slaves is proof
of this kingdom's prosperity.
Why do you run?
なぜ　お主は逃げるのだ
If you guietly submit to being a slave,
you will never want for food.
おとなしく奴隷になれば　食べるのには困らぬぞ
少なくともルシタニアより　よい暮らしができるであろう…
At the very least, you would have
a better life than back in Lusitania...
What did you say?!
なんだと　我が国が貧しいというのか
Are you saying my kingdom is poor?!
Uh, well, when children such as
yourself are heading off to war...
ああいや　こんな子供が戦に出るほどだから…
I'm no child! I'm eleven years old already!
子供ではない　もう１１歳だ
Eleven?! The same as I! You are a child!
１１　私と一緒　やはり　子供ではないか
By this age, we are full-fledged warriors!
この年になれば　立派な戦士だろうが
We devote ourselves in the
service of the God of Yaldabaoth
我らイアルダボート神に忠誠を尽くし
異教徒を根絶やしにするのだ
and we will wipe out the heathens!
Why do you so despise
those who do not believe?
なぜ　そこまで異教徒を憎む
我らが神は　人を平等に扱う
Our god treats all men as equals.
But look at you people.
だが　貴様らはどうだ
You place people beneath other people.
人の下に人を置く　あの奴隷制度はなんだ
こらっ　なんにやってんだ
--Hey! What are you doing?!
--What the hell is this system of slavery?!
Our god will not stand for such things.
我らの神は　そのようなことは許さない
人は皆　平等だ
All men are equal!
Therefore, you heathens,
who do not follow our god's teachings,
よって　我らの神の教えに従わぬ貴様ら異教徒は
may be treated as different and killed!
差別し　殺してもいい
That is utterly illogical.
支離滅裂だ
貴様
--You bastard!
--Oh, no...
ああ　いや
いたぞ
There he is!
Oh, not again!
また
ll people would just embrace the God of Yaldaba
全ての人がイアルダボート神を信仰すれば
there would be no fighting to begin with!
そもそも争いなど起こらん　分かるか
Do you understand that?!
どうせ　何も考えずに育ったのだろう
You probably grew up without
a thought in your head.
Damn ignorant pampered boy!
世間知らずのお坊ちゃんめ　親の顔が見たいわ
The parents you must have!
Stop!
待て
What do you suppose could be going on?
なんでございましょう
There seems to be a commotion down below...
下の方が慌しいようですが
I have returned, Tahamenay.
戻ったぞ　タハミーネ
留守の間　変わりなかったか
Has all remained unchanged in my absence?
Why not at least divest yourself of your armor?
鎧くらい　お脱ぎになっては
土産だ　よい絹が手に入った
Gifts.
I obtained some fine silks--
Is that so?
そうですか　そこに置いておいてください
Please leave them there.
I will come again.
また来る
The west rampart! Don't let him get away!
西の城壁だ　逃がすな
Your Highness!
殿下
Faster!
早く
痛て…
寄るな
Don't come any closer!
この者が　どうなってもいいのか
You don't want anything
to happen to him, do you?!
Looks like this is it.
もはや　ここまでか
Surrender yourself. Do not die needlessly.
投降せよ　無駄死にはするな
殿下
Your Highness!
なんだ
What was that?
ダリューン
Daryun!
You fell from up there?
上から落ちたのか
大丈夫かい
Are you all right?
There's one more.
もう一人だ
Come on, up we go.
そらっ　せぇ～の
There.
よし
Hey! He...
おい　あいつ
馬泥棒　おい　待て
Horse thief!
Stop!
ダリューン
Daryun!
Hey, you...
あんた
ダリューン　待て
Daryun, wait!
アルスラーン殿下　おケガは
Prince Arslan, are you injured?
ダリューン　大丈夫だ
Daryun, I am fine.
だから　俺の馬　捕まえてくれ
Why did you stop me from shooting him?
なぜ　あの者を討つことをお止めになったのです
落ち着いて
いや　つい…
Well...
It just happened...
分かりました　私が討ち損じたことにしておきます
I understand. We will say
that I failed to find my target.
Really, thank goodness that he's all right.
本当に無事でよかったねぇ
捕虜に捕まって　振り回されたって
Captured by a prisoner and dragged
along on a wild-goose chase, huh?
危ねぇなぁ
That's so dangerous.
What on earth is the prince doing?
何やってんだか　王子は
Please be a little more careful!
もう少し　お気をつけください
一歩間違えば　殺されてましたぞ
One misstep and you could have been killed!
それを言われると…
When you put it that way...
王太子殿下
Your Royal Highness.
We have captured the three whose
actions resulted in the prisoner's escape.
捕虜の脱走の原因を作った３名を捕らえてまいりました
殿下
--Your Highness!
--We are so sorry!
申し訳ありません
お許しください　殿下
Please forgive them, Your Highness!
罰なら　私たちに
Punish us instead!
We beg of you to show leniency
towards our children!
子供たちには　何とぞ寛大な処置を
Control yourselves!
控え
It was because of them that
His Highness's life was put at risk!
こいつらのせいで　殿下のお命が危険にさらされたのだぞ
It is fine. Release them.
よい　放してやれ
No! It would set a bad examp...
ならん　示しが…
殿下
Your Highness!
All are safe. That is enough.
無事なら　それでよい
頼んだぞ
Take care of it for me.
Yes, sir!
はっ
ありがとうございます
Thank you very much!
When I grow up, I'll join the cavalry,
no matter what I have to do,
俺　大きくなったら　絶対騎兵隊に入って　殿下にお仕えします
to be in your service, Your Highness.
Yeah.
Me, too.
俺も
Everyone, stay safe.
みんな　無事でいろ
必ず助けに戻るぞ
I'll be back to rescue you, I promise.
馬を持ってまいります
I will bring you a horse.
The things he had to say
あの者の話は　王宮で教えられたものと違って面白かったな
were interesting and different from
what I have been taught at the palace.
I want to hear what the other captive
Lusitanians have to say as well.
囚われている他のルシタニア人にも　話を聞きたいな
Come on! Hurry up and carry them away!
さっさと運べ
That is...
あれは…
お…王子
M-My prince?!
Hey!
早くしろ
Make it quick!
殿下
Your Highness!
Why?!
なぜ
なりません　このような汚らわしい所に
You must not be here in this filthy place.
You killed them?
殺してしまったのか
はい
Yes...
They were unruly and there was
nothing to be done with them.
暴れてどうにもなりませんでしたので
Lusitanians are the same as animals.
ルシタニア人など　獣と同じです
There's no taming them.
飼いならすことはできませんよ
ほら　急げ
Come on, hurry up.
Those men...
あの者たち　素直に奴隷になっておれば
If they had quietly accepted becoming slaves,
they would not have lost their lives...
命を落とさなかったものを…
Why?
なぜなのだ
Your Highness...
殿下　いつか殿下がご即位なされましたら
Someday, when you have
ascended to the throne,
登用していただきたい我が友人がおります
there is a friend of mine that
I would like for you to appoint.
That man may be able to answer
Your Highness's questions.
その者なら　殿下の疑問に答えられるかもしれません
それは誰だ
Who is this man?
Oh, uh, no...
ああ　いや
口が滑りました
That was a thoughtless remark.
He is a crotchety man,
so please forget that I said anything.
そやつはひねくれ者ゆえ　今の話はなかったことに
Well, now you have me wondering.
なんだ　思わせぶりな
まだ　この先　何十年も父上の王位は揺るがぬだろう
My lord father's reign is unlikely
to waver for many decades to come.
I cannot yet even begin to
imagine ascending to the throne.
私が即位することなど　まだ想像もつかぬ
As long as my lord father is here,
our kingdom of Pars will be secure.
父上がおれば　我がパルスは安泰だ
It seems it will be a while
before I get to meet your friend.
お主の友人とやらには　しばらく会えそうにないな
Yes.
ええ
だが　これより３年後
However, three years hence,
the Royal Capital of Ecbatana
would be shrouded in fire and blood.
王都エクバターナは　炎と血煙に包まれることとなる
Maryam, their ally kingdom,
would fall before Lusitania's invasion.
ルシタニアの侵略により　盟邦マルヤム王国は滅亡
And that onslaught would
finally reach as far as Pars.
その進撃は　ついにパルスにも及んだ
Pars Era, the year 320, autumn.
パルス暦３２０年　秋
王太子アルスラーン　時に１４歳
At the age of fourteen, Crown Prince Arslan...
...embarks upon his maiden battle.
初陣す
The azure crescent moon
wheels across the night sky
The glittering world transcends the clouds
With this journey’s beginning that you dance now
Off into the yonder wishes go, drifting
When a tale that is shapeless
Spreads across the moonlight
The treasure that is within you
Melts away into the wind now
Tomorrow, try to take
wing as your unvarnished self
Sometime, somewhere,
you wanted this, remember?
You can hear it, can ’t you?
There, that shining dream from that day
The azure crescent moon
wheels across the night sky
The glittering world transcends the clouds
With this journeyﬁs beginning that you dance now
Off into the yonder wishes go
風が翻り　霧が流れた
The wind changed and the fog rolled in.
It seemed an auspicious omen to Arslan.
吉兆であるように　アルスラーンには思えた
次回
"Chapter II
Age Fourteen, Maiden Battle"
Next time, "Age Fourteen, Maiden Battle."
And thus, the boy would become king.
少年は　そして王となる